Let's look together at a second
example: the check-order one.
In this case, we have only one shared variable
called turn. Its value represents which thread
is allowed to enter the critical section.
The entry section of each thread does a
busywait loop until it does not
see its id in the variable turn.
Once it completes its critical section, each
thread sets the value of the other thread into
the variable turn. When A is done it allows B
to enter the critical section and vice-versa.
Is this a valid solution to
the critical section problem?
Let's start by checking the mutual exclusion
property, in the same case we were looking
at before, that of A entering its critical
section while B is in its critical section.
Before entering its critical section,
A must see that turn's value is A.
Can B see the value of turn
being "B" during this period?
The answer is no because A will set it
to B only after the critical section.
Notice that if you think it could because you
are considering the case in which the period
in which A's critical section happens is here,
then you are considering a portion of time during
which the execution is valid, but the case we are
looking at needs still to be explored assuming A
sees turn value being A after B completes line 4.
Now that we know that A cannot enter its critical
section while B is in it, we need to check if B
can enter its critical section while A is in it.
If you think about this, you can immediately
conclude that this can be shown with the same
example, by switching A with
B, so the answer is still no.
Good, we have proven we cannot find an
example that breaks mutual exclusion.
Let's check the progress property now.
Can one of the threads be willing to enter the
critical section but unable to do that while the
other thread is also outside its critical section?
For instance, let's say A is in its
waiting loop because turn's value is B.
Can it happen that B does not put turn
value to A in a bounded time? Yes,
B can be in its remainder section and, as we
said, the duration of the reminder section
is arbitrarily long, which means
the progress property is violated.
We can then conclude this code is not a valid
solution to the critical section problem,
because it breaks the progress property.